I'm here to talk to you about how globalized we are,
انا هنا اليوم لأتحدث لكم عن مستوى العولمة الذي نحن فيه
how globalized we aren't,
ومستوى عدم العولمة (القوقعة) الذي نحن فيه
and why it's important to actually be accurate
ولماذا يفترض ان نكون دقيقين
in making those kinds of assessments.
في وضع هذه التقييمات
And the leading point of view on this, whether measured
ووجهة النظر الرئيسية لهذا ، سواءً قيست
by number of books sold, mentions in media,
بعدد الكتب المباعة، او ما يقال في الاعلام
or surveys that I've run with groups ranging from
او حتى الاستبيانات التي قمت باجرائها بين
my students to delegates to the World Trade Organization,
طلابي ومندوبي منظمة التجارة العالمية
is this view that national borders
هو هذه النظرة ان الحدود بين الدول
really don't matter very much anymore,
لم تعد ذات اهمية
cross-border integration is close to complete,
فالتداخل بين الحدود اصبح كاملا
and we live in one world.
ونحن نعيش في عالم واحد.
And what's interesting about this view
ما هو مشوق في وجهة النظر هذه
is, again, it's a view that's held by pro-globalizers
هو، مرة اخرى، نظرة الموالين للعولمة
like Tom Friedman, from whose book this quote is obviously excerpted,
من امثال (توم فريدمان ) صاحب الكتاب المشوق
but it's also held by anti-globalizers, who see this giant
بل وايضا المناوئين للعولمة الذين يرون ان العولمة مثل
globalization tsunami that's about to wreck all our lives
موجة تسونامي عملاقة قادمة لتدمرنا كلنا
if it hasn't already done so.
اذا لم يكن هذا قد حدث بالفعل
The other thing I would add is that this is not a new view.
الشيء الاخر الذي اود ان اضيفة هو ان هذه ليست نظرة جديدة
I'm a little bit of an amateur historian, so I've spent
انا شبيه بمؤرخ مبتدئ، لذا قمت
some time going back, trying to see the first mention
بالعودة الى الماضي قليلا، محاولا البحث عن اول مرة تم
of this kind of thing. And the best, earliest quote
ذكر شيء كهذا. وافضل واقدم ما وجدته
that I could find was one from David Livingstone,
كان من (دبفيد ليفينجستون)
writing in the 1850s about how the railroad, the steam ship,
وقد كتب حوالي عام 1850م عن كيفية ان القطارات، السفن البخارية
and the telegraph were integrating East Africa perfectly
و التليغراف قد ربطت شرق افريقيا تماما
with the rest of the world.
ببقية العالم
Now clearly, David Livingstone
وكما هو واضح الان فإن (ديفيد ليفنجستون)
was a little bit ahead of his time,
كان متقدما على عصره
but it does seem useful to ask ourselves,
لكن يبدو انه من المهم ان نسأل انفسنا
"Just how global are we?"
" كم نحن مترابطون عالميا"
before we think about where we go from here.
قبل ان نفكر في الى اين سنتقدم من هنا
So the best way I've found of trying to get people
لذا وجدت ان افضل طريقة لجعل الناس
to take seriously the idea that the world may not be flat,
يتحدثون بجدية فكرة ان هذا العالم قد لا يكون مسطحا
may not even be close to flat, is with some data.
وقد لا يكون شبيه بمسطح. هو ببعض البيانات
So one of the things I've been doing over the last few years
لذا فأحد الاشياء التي حاولت القيام بها خلال الاعوام الماضية
is really compiling data on things that could either happen
هو جمع بيانات عن اشياء قد تحدث
within national borders or across national borders,
داخل الحدود الدولية او خارجها،
and I've looked at the cross-border component
وقد بحثت في ما قد يحدث خارج الحدود
as a percentage of the total.
كنسبة مئوية من الكل
I'm not going to present all the data that I have here today,
لن اقوم بعرض كل البيانات التي بحوزتي اليوم
but let me just give you a few data points.
ولكن سأعرض بعضها فقط
I'm going to talk a little bit about one kind of information flow,
سأتحدث قليلا عن احد انواع تدفق المعلومات,
one kind of flow of people, one kind of flow of capital,
احد انواع تدفق الناس, ونوع واحد من تدفق رأس المال
and, of course, trade in products and services.
وبالطبع تجارة الخدمات والمنتجات
So let's start off with plain old telephone service.
اذن فلنبدء بخدمة الاتصالات الهاتفية.
Of all the voice-calling minutes in the world last year,
من كل المحادثات الصوتية في العالم خلال العام الماضي
what percentage do you think were accounted for
كم تعتقدون ان النسبة المئوية
by cross-border phone calls?
للمحادثات الدولية
Pick a percentage in your own mind.
ضع اي نسبة من خيالك
The answer turns out to be two percent.
الاجابة هي نسبة 2 بالمئة
If you include Internet telephony, you might be able
واذا اضفنا خدمة الإنترنت قد نستطيع
to push this number up to six or seven percent,
ان نرفع هذه النسبة الى 6 او 7 بالمئة
but it's nowhere near what people tend to estimate.
ولكن نجد ان هذا الرقم لا يقارب ما يتوقعه الناس
Or let's turn to people moving across borders.
فلننتقل الى البشر الذين يعبرون الحدود
One particular thing we might look at, in terms of
النقطة الاساسية هنا التي نركز فيها،
long-term flows of people, is what percentage
تدفق الناس على المدى الطويل اي الهجرة، ما هي نسبة
of the world's population is accounted for
انتقال افراد من الجيل الاول مقارنة مع عدد سكان العالم للهجرة
by first-generation immigrants?
مع عدد سكان العالم للهجرة؟
Again, please pick a percentage.
مرة اخرى ارجو ان تخمنوا النسبة
Turns out to be a little bit higher.
انها اكثر قليلاً
It's actually about three percent.
في الحقيقة انها تقارب الـ 3 بالمئة
Or think of investment. Take all the real investment
فلننظر الى الاستثمارات، فلنأخذ جميع الاستثمارات الحقيقية
that went on in the world in 2010.
التي حدثت في عام 2010
What percentage of that was accounted for
ما هي النسبة المتوقعة
by foreign direct investment?
للاستثمارات الاجنبية المباشرة
Not quite ten percent.
لا تصل حتى لعشرة بالمئة
And then finally, the one statistic
واخيراً، الإحصائية
that I suspect many of the people in this room have seen:
التي اتوقع ان عددا من الاشخاص في هذه الغرفة قد رأوها:
the export-to-GDP ratio.
نسبة التصدير مقارنة باجمالي الناتج المحلي
If you look at the official statistics, they typically indicate
اذا القينا نظرة على الاحصائيات الرسمية فهي توضح
a little bit above 30 percent.
ان النسبة تفوق قليلا الثلاثين بالمئة
However, there's a big problem with the official statistics,
إلا اننا نجد ان هنالك عيبا كبيرا في الاحصائيات الرسمية
in that if, for instance, a Japanese component supplier
وكمثال اذا قام منتج ياباني بارسال شيء
ships something to China to be put into an iPod,
الى الصين ليضعوه في اجهزة iPod
and then the iPod gets shipped to the U.S.,
ثم تم ارسال الـ iPod الى الولايات المتحدة
that component ends up getting counted multiple times.
سيتم حساب ذلك المنتج عدة مرات
So nobody knows how bad this bias
لذا لا يوجد احد يعرف مدى سوء التأثير على
with the official statistics actually is, so I thought I would
الحصائيات الرسمية، لذا فكرت
ask the person who's spearheading the effort
ان اسأل الشخص الذي بذل الجهد
to generate data on this, Pascal Lamy,
لاخراج هذه البيانات وهو (باسكال لامي)
the Director of the World Trade Organization,
مدير منظمة التجارة العالمية
what his best guess would be
عن افضل تخمين له
of exports as a percentage of GDP,
عن نسبة اجمالي الناتج المحلي مقارنة بالتصدير
without the double- and triple-counting,
اذا حذفنا العد المزدوج او اكثر من ذلك
and it's actually probably a bit under 20 percent, rather than
اتضح عندها ان النسبة هي اقل من عشرين بالمئة بشيء بسيط وليست
the 30 percent-plus numbers that we're talking about.
الرقم السابق وهو اكثر من ثلاثون بالمئة
So it's very clear that if you look at these numbers
لذا فمن الواضح بعد الاطلاع على تلك الارقام
or all the other numbers that I talk about in my book,
او الارقام الاخرى التي تحدثت عنها في كتابي
"World 3.0," that we're very, very far from
" العالم 3.0" اننا بعيدين جدا جدا
the no-border effect benchmark, which would imply
عن نقطة ان العالم اصبح بلا حدود، بما يوضح
internationalization levels of the order of 85, 90, 95 percent.
ان نسب 85، 90، 95 بالمئة الني كان يتنبئون بها عن العولمة
So clearly, apocalyptically-minded authors
لذا وبشكل واضح فان الكتاب الذين يبالغون بشكل كبير
have overstated the case.
قاموا بتضخيم الحقائق بشكل كبير.
But it's not just the apocalyptics, as I think of them,
ولكن ليسو هم فقط،
who are prone to this kind of overstatement.
الذين يقومون بتضخيم الامور.
I've also spent some time surveying audiences
قمت ايضا بعمل مسح للجماهير
in different parts of the world
في اماكن مختلفة من العالم
on what they actually guess these numbers to be.
عن ما يتوقعونه من ارقام
Let me share with you the results of a survey
دعوني اشارككم بنتائج ذلك المسح
that Harvard Business Review was kind enough to run
الذي قامت مجلة هارفرد بزنس ريفيو بطرحه
of its readership as to what people's guesses
عن العلاقة بين توقعات الناس
along these dimensions actually were.
و الارقام الحقيقية
So a couple of observations stand out for me from this slide.
بعض الارقام اختلفت عن هذه الشريحة
First of all, there is a suggestion of some error.
أولا، كان هناك اعتقاد بوجود خطأ بسيط
Okay. (Laughter)
حسنا (تصفيق)
Second, these are pretty large errors. For four quantities
ثانيا، هناك اخطاء كبيرة لأربعة اسئلة
whose average value is less than 10 percent,
والذي يقدر متوسطه بأقل من عشرة بالمائة
you have people guessing three, four times that level.
هناك من يتوقع ثلاثة او اربعة اضعاف تلك المستويات
Even though I'm an economist, I find that
وعلى الرغم من انني خبير اقتصادي ، فقد وجدت
a pretty large error.
ان هنالك فارقا كبيرا
And third, this is not just confined to the readers
وثالثا، وهذا ليس مخصص لقراء
of the Harvard Business Review.
هارفرد بيزنس ريفيو (مجلة هارفرد الاقتصادية )
I've run several dozen such surveys in different parts
فقد قامت بعدد من الدرزينات من تلك المسوحات في
of the world, and in all cases except one,
بقاع مختلفة من العالم، وفي كل الحالات ما عدا واحدة
where a group actually underestimated
قامت مجموعة بتوقع ارقام اقل
the trade-to-GDP ratio, people have this tendency
لمقارنة نسبة اجمالي الناتج المحلي مقارنة بالتصدير. فالناس لديهم هذا الميل
towards overestimation, and so I thought it important
نحو المبالغة، وحتى ظننت أنه من المهم
to give a name to this, and that's what I refer to
عمل تسمية لهذا الأمر، وهذا ما قمت بتسميته
as globaloney, the difference between the dark blue bars
بـ جلوبلوني (العولمة الوهمية)، الفرق بين الاشرطة الزرقاء
and the light gray bars.
والاشرطة الرمادية
Especially because, I suspect, some of you may still be
خصوصا لأنه، وانا اشك، ان بعضكم قد يكون
a little bit skeptical of the claims, I think it's important
لايزال مشككا بالإدعاءات، اعتقد انه من المهم
to just spend a little bit of time thinking about
امضاء بعض الوقت في التفكير
why we might be prone to globaloney.
في ان قد نكون معرضين للجلوبلوني (العولمة الوهمية)
A couple of different reasons come to mind.
سببين اخرين خطرا في ذهني
First of all, there's a real dearth of data in the debate.
اولا ان هناك ندرة حقيقية للبيانات في المناقشة.
Let me give you an example. When I first published
دعوني اعطيكم مثالا. حين قمت سابقا بطرح
some of these data a few years ago
بعض هذه البيانات قبل عدة سنوات
in a magazine called Foreign Policy,
في مجلة اسمها فورين بوليسي (السياسة الخارجية)
one of the people who wrote in, not entirely in agreement,
قام احد الاشخاص بالرد وهو لم يكن موافقا بالكامل
was Tom Friedman. And since my article was titled
كان توم فريدمان. وبما ان مقالي كان معنونا بـ
"Why the World Isn't Flat," that wasn't too surprising. (Laughter)
" لماذا ان العالم غير مسطح" وهذا لم يكن مفاجئا تماما
What was very surprising to me was Tom's critique,
ما كان مفاجئا هو النقد الذي قدمه توم
which was, "Ghemawat's data are narrow."
والذي كان " البيانات التي قدمها جيماوات قليلة"
And this caused me to scratch my head, because
وهذا دعاني للتفكير، لأنه
as I went back through his several-hundred-page book,
عندما قمت بقرائة كتابة الذي يحوي مئات الصفحات
I couldn't find a single figure, chart, table,
لم اجد اي رقم،رسم بياني، جدول،
reference or footnote.
مرجع او شرح في اسفل الصفحة
So my point is, I haven't presented a lot of data here
لذا فالنقطة التي اقصدها، هو انني لم اقم بعرض يبانات كثيرة هنا
to convince you that I'm right, but I would urge you
لأقنعكم انني على صواب، بل انني اشجعكم
to go away and look for your own data
للذهاب والبحث عن اي بيانات تجدونها انتم
to try and actually assess whether some of these
وان تحاولوا ان توجهوا بعض هذه
hand-me-down insights that we've been bombarded with
التي اطلعتكم عليها الان
actually are correct.
هي في الحقيقة صواب
So dearth of data in the debate is one reason.
اذن فقلة المعلومات للمناقشة هو احد الاسباب
A second reason has to do with peer pressure.
والسبب الثاني له علاقة مع ضغط الأقران
I remember, I decided to write my
اذكر انه حين قررت كتابة مقالي
"Why the World Isn't Flat" article, because
"لماذا ان العالم ليس مسطح" بسبب
I was being interviewed on TV in Mumbai,
انه تم عمل مقابلة تلفزيونية معي في بومباي
and the interviewer's first question to me was,
وكان اول سؤال طرحته علي مقدمة البرنامج هو:
"Professor Ghemawat, why do you still believe
" بروفيسور جيماوات، لماذا لازلت تصدق
that the world is round?" And I started laughing,
بان العالم مستدير؟" فبدأت بالضحك
because I hadn't come across that formulation before. (Laughter)
لأنه لم تمر علي هذه الصيغة قبل ذلك ( ضحك )
And as I was laughing, I was thinking,
وحين كنت اضحك، فكرت
I really need a more coherent response, especially
أنني فعلا بحاجة لاستجابة أكثر انسجاما، خصوصا
on national TV. I'd better write something about this. (Laughter)
على التلفزيون القومي. لابد ان اقوم بالكتابة عن هذا الموضوع ( ضحك)
But what I can't quite capture for you
لكن ما لا استطيع وصفه لكم
was the pity and disbelief
هو مقدار الشفقة وعدم التصديق
with which the interviewer asked her question.
الذي كان واضحا في سؤال مقدمة البرنامج
The perspective was, here is this poor professor.
كان في منظورها، ياله من بروفيسور مسكين
He's clearly been in a cave for the last 20,000 years.
من الواضح انه كان يعيش في كهف خلال العشرين الف عاما الماضية
He really has no idea
انه حقا لا يعرف شيئا
as to what's actually going on in the world.
عن ما يحدث في العالم
So try this out with your friends and acquaintances,
لذا حاولوا مناقشة ذلك مع اصدقائكم ومعارفكم
if you like. You'll find that it's very cool
اذا اردتم. ستجدون انه من المسلي جدا الحديث عن ان
to talk about the world being one, etc.
العالم اصبح واحدا, وما الى ذلك
If you raise questions about that formulation,
اذا قمت باثارة تساؤلات بتلك الصيغة
you really are considered a bit of an antique.
فانت تصنف انك عتيق الى حد ما
And then the final reason, which I mention,
والسبب الاخير الذي سأعرضه
especially to a TED audience, with some trepidation,
لمتابعي TED ببعض الخوف
has to do with what I call "techno-trances."
ما ادعوه بـتكنو ترانسيس ( غيبوبة التكنولوجيا)
If you listen to techno music for long periods of time,
فاذا كنت تستمع لموسيقى التكنو لفترة طويلة
it does things to your brainwave activity. (Laughter)
فهي تقوم بعمل شيء ما في موجات دماغك (ضحك)
Something similar seems to happen
شيء مشابه لذلك يبدو انه يحدث
with exaggerated conceptions of how technology
مع المفاهيم المبالغ فيها عن الكيفية التي ستقوم التكنولوجيا
is going to overpower in the very immediate run
بالتغلب بشكل سريع جدا على
all cultural barriers, all political barriers,
كل العوائق الثقافية، كل العوائق السياسية
all geographic barriers, because at this point
كل العوائق الجغرافية
I know you aren't allowed to ask me questions,
لأنه في هذه النقطة واعلم انه لا يمكنكم طرح اي اسئلة علي
but when I get to this point in my lecture with my students,
لكن حين اصل لهذه النقطة مع تلاميذي
hands go up, and people ask me,
ترتفع الايادي، ويسئلني الطلبة
"Yeah, but what about Facebook?"
"حقا، وماذا إذا عن فيسبوك "
And I got this question often enough that I thought
اتلقى هذا السؤال بشكل كبير حتى فكرت
I'd better do some research on Facebook.
بانه من الافضل ان ابحث في موضوع الفيس بوك هذا
Because, in some sense, it's the ideal kind of technology
وذلك انه بشكل ما فهو الشكل الامثل للتكنولوجيا
to think about. Theoretically, it makes it
التي يفكر بها، نظريا من السهل جدا
as easy to form friendships halfway around the world
عمل صداقة مع شخص عبر العالم
as opposed to right next door.
كما لو انه جارك
What percentage of people's friends on Facebook
ما هي نسبة الاصدقاء في فيسبوك
are actually located in countries other than where
الذين يعيشون في بلدان غير تلك التي يقيم
people we're analyzing are based?
فيها الافراد محل البحث؟
The answer is probably somewhere between
الجواب تقريبا هو بين
10 to 15 percent.
10 الى 15 بالمئة
Non-negligible, so we don't live in an entirely local
شئ لا يذكر، لذا نحن لا نعيش حاليا في عالم محلي
or national world, but very, very far from the 95 percent level
ولكن بعيد جدا عن نسبة 95 بالمئة
that you would expect, and the reason's very simple.
التي قد تتوقعها، والسبب في ذلك بسيط جدا
We don't, or I hope we don't, form friendships at random
اننا لا نقوم او اتمنى اننا لا نقوم بعمل صداقات عشوائية
on Facebook. The technology is overlaid
على الفيسبوك. التكنولوجيا مطروحة امامنا
on a pre-existing matrix of relationships that we have,
على مصفوفة من العلاقات الحقيقية التي نملكها
and those relationships are what the technology
وهذه العلاقات لا تقوم التكنولوجيا
doesn't quite displace. Those relationships are why
باستبدالها. وهذه العلاقات هي السبب في
we get far fewer than 95 percent of our friends
ان نسبه الاصدقاء في بلدان غير التي نعيش فيها
being located in countries other than where we are.
اقل بكثير من 95 بالمئة
So does all this matter? Or is globaloney
إذن هل هذا الامر مهم؟ ام ان الجلوبلوني
just a harmless way of getting people to pay more attention
هي طريقة غير ضارة لجعل الناس يهتمون قليلا
to globalization-related issues?
بالمواضيع المتعلقة بالعولمة؟
I want to suggest that actually,
انا اعتقد ان الجلوبلوني
globaloney can be very harmful to your health.
هي ضارة جدا بالصحة
First of all, recognizing that the glass
ففي البداية، فمعرفة ان الكوب
is only 10 to 20 percent full is critical to seeing
ممتلئ فقط بنسبة 10 الى 20 بالمئة هو هام جدا لمعرفة
that there might be potential for additional gains
انه قد يكون هنالك احتمال لمكاسب اضافية
from additional integration,
من اندماجات اضافية
whereas if we thought we were already there,
سواء اعتقدنا اننا وصلنا لتلك النقطة بالفعل
there would be no particular point to pushing harder.
لن يكون هناك فائدة معينة للبدء والتقدم بعد ذلك.
It's a little bit like, we wouldn't be having a conference
كما لو انه، سوف لن نقوم بعمل مؤتمر
on radical openness if we already thought we were totally open
نتحدث فيه عن الانفتاحات الجذرية اذا كنا بالفعل منفتحين لكل
to all the kinds of influences that are being talked about
انواع التأثيرات التي تحدثنا عنها
at this conference.
خلال هذا المؤتمر
So being accurate about how limited globalization levels are
لذا ان نكون دقيقين عن مدى محدودية مستويات العولمة
is critical to even being able to notice
هو هام جدا لملاحظة
that there might be room for something more,
انه قد يكون هناك مكان لشيء اخر
something that would contribute further to global welfare.
شيء من شأنه أن يسهم أيضا في تحقيق الرفاه العالمي.
Which brings me to my second point.
وهذا يقودني للنقطة الثانية
Avoiding overstatement is also very helpful
ان تجنب المبالغة هو شيء مفيد جدا
because it reduces and in some cases even reverses
لأنه يقلل وأحيانا يعكس
some of the fears that people have about globalization.
بعض المخاوف التي لدى الناس من العولمة
So I actually spend most of my "World 3.0" book
لذا فقد كان معظم عملي في كتابي " 3.0 العالم "
working through a litany of market failures and fears
في سلسلة من إخفاقات السوق والمخاوف
that people have that they worry globalization is going to exacerbate.
التي لدى الناس من ان العولمة سوف تؤدي الى التفاقم
I'm obviously not going to be able to do that for you today,
ومن الواضح انني لن اتمكن من فعل هذا اليوم
so let me just present to you two headlines
لذا دعوني فقط اعرض عليكم عنوانين رئيسيين
as an illustration of what I have in mind.
كمثال على ما يخطر ببالي
Think of France and the current debate about immigration.
فكروا في فرنسا والجدل الجاري حاليا عن الهجرة
When you ask people in France what percentage
فحين تسأل الفرنسيين عن نسبة
of the French population is immigrants,
المهاجرين في فرنسا
the answer is about 24 percent. That's their guess.
سيكون الجواب حوالي 24 بالمئة. وهذا افتراضهم
Maybe realizing that the number is just eight percent
وهنالك احتمال انه عند معرفة ان الرقم هو فقط 8 بالمئة
might help cool some of the superheated rhetoric
قد يؤدي ذلك لتهدئة لهجة خطب الكراهية الرنانة
that we see around the immigration issue.
التي نراها في المواضيع المتعلقة بالهجرة
Or to take an even more striking example,
او لنأخذ موضوعا اخر اكثر اثارة
when the Chicago Council on Foreign Relations
حين قام مجلس العلاقات الخارجية في شيكاغو
did a survey of Americans, asking them to guess
بعمل استبيان للامريكيين يطلب منهم فيه ان يخمنوا
what percentage of the federal budget went to foreign aid,
نسبة المعونات الخارجية التي اخذت من الميزانية الفيدرالية
the guess was 30 percent, which is
وكان تخمينهم 30 بالمئة وهو
slightly in excess of the actual level — ("actually about ... 1%") (Laughter) —
يفوق بشكل بسيط النسبة الحقيقية (النسبة الحقيقية 1 بالمئة )
of U.S. governmental commitments to federal aid.
التزامات الحكومة الامريكية للمعونة الفيدرالية
The reassuring thing about this particular survey was,
الشيء المطمئن في هذا الاستبيان كان
when it was pointed out to people how far
عند معرفة الناس بأن النسبة التي خمنوها
their estimates were from the actual data,
كانت ابعد كثرا من الواقع
some of them — not all of them — seemed to become
قام بعضهم وليس كلهم
more willing to consider increases in foreign aid.
بإبداء الرغبة في زيادة المعونات الخارجية
So foreign aid is actually a great way
اذن فالعون الخارجي هو موضوع جيد
of sort of wrapping up here, because
لختام موضوعنا هنا. لأنه
if you think about it, what I've been talking about today
اذا فكرتم في ما تحدثت عنه اليوم وهو الفكرة
is this notion -- very uncontroversial amongst economists --
وهي غير مثيرة نهائيا بالنسبة للاقتصاديين
that most things are very home-biased.
هو ان معظم الاشياء متحيزة للداخل
"Foreign aid is the most aid to poor people,"
فالمعونة الخارجية هي معظم المعونة التي يتحصل عليها الفقراء
is about the most home-biased thing you can find.
انه اكثر شيء منحاز للداخل يمكن ان تجده
If you look at the OECD countries and how much
اذا نظرنا الى دول منظمة التعاون الاقتصادي وكم
they spend per domestic poor person,
مقدار صرفهم على الفقراء في بلدانهم ا
and compare it with how much they spend
ومقارنة ذلك مقدار صرفهم
per poor person in poor countries,
على الفقراء في الدول الفقيرة،
the ratio — Branko Milanovic at the World Bank did the calculations —
فان النسبة ( وقد قم بالحسابات برانكو ميلانوفيتش من البنك الدولي )
turns out to be about 30,000 to one.
تبين ان الفرق هو 30000 مفابل واحد
Now of course, some of us, if we truly are cosmopolitan,
وبالطبع فان بعضنا اذا كنا حقا مناصرين للعولمة
would like to see that ratio being brought down
فسنود ان نرى هذه النسبة
to one-is-to-one.
واحد لواحد
I'd like to make the suggestion that we don't need to aim
افترض انه لا يوجد داعي لتوجيه
for that to make substantial progress from where we are.
انفسنا لعمل هذا التغير الكيبر
If we simply brought that ratio down to 15,000 to one,
فاذا فقط قمنا بتوصيل النسبة الى 15000 مقابل واحد
we would be meeting those aid targets that were agreed
سنصل الى تلك النقاط التي اتفقنا عليها
at the Rio Summit 20 years ago that the summit
في قمة " ريو " قبل عشرين عاما
that ended last week made no further progress on.
والذي لم تقم القمة التي انتهت الاسبوع الماضي باضافة شيء اليه
So in summary, while radical openness is great,
لذلك وباختصار. بينما ان الانفتاحات الجذرية رائعة
given how closed we are,
واننا قربيون جدا
even incremental openness could make things
بل وحتى الانفتاحات التدرجية بامكانها عمل فارض كبير للافضل
dramatically better. Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم (تصفيق )
(Applause)
(تصفيق)